Guide to the Charles N. Hunter Papers, 1850s-1932 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Charles N. Hunter papers 1850s-1932 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Hunter, Charles N., circa 1851-1931
7.3 Linear Feet
Black educator, journalist, and reformer from Raleigh, North Carolina.
Correspondence, scrapbooks of clippings, print material such as articles and reports, and other papers, all dating from the Civil War into the first few decades of the 20th century. Includes a fourth edition of Lunsford Lane's slave narrative. The material discusses and illuminates the problems experienced by emancipated blacks during Reconstruction and into the early 20th century, encompassing agriculture, business, race relations, reconstruction, education, politics, voting rights, and economic improvement for African Americans. Other topics include Durham and Raleigh, N.C. history; the temperance movement, Hunter's personal matters and family finances, the North Carolina Industrial Association, and the N.C. Negro State Fair. Significant correspondents include Charles B. Aycock, Thomas W. Bickett, William E. Borah, Craig Locke, Josephus Daniels, W.E.B. Du Bois, Charles G. Dawes, John A. Logan, Lee S. Overman, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Theodore Roosevelt, Charles Sumner, Zebulon B. Vance, and Booker T. Washington. There is also correpondence from two early African American Congressmen, Henry P. Cheatham and George H. White. Also included is a draft of a speech given by Frederick Douglass in 1880 at the 2nd Negro State Fair.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Charles N. Hunter Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1941.
Biographical Note
Charles Norfleet Hunter was born of slave parentage in the early 1850s in Raleigh, North Carolina. Hunter was the son of artisan Osborne Hunter, slave of William Dallas Haywood, a member of one of Raleigh’s most prominent families. Hunter’s mother died when he was three and he was raised by an aunt. Hunter was prominent in efforts to provide better educational facilities and curriculum for African Americans in North Carolina and was instrumental in constructing several schools for African Americans in the state. He served as principal for many schools in the state and served as editor of several newspapers and publications. As a member of the North Carolina Industrial Association, he also sought to expand the opportunities for African Americans in agriculture and industry.
Chronology List
circa 1851 Born of slave parents, Osborne and Mary Hunter, in Raleigh, N.C.
1869-1874 Employed at Raleigh Branch Freedman's Savings Bank; assistant cashier by 1874, when the bank failed
1875 Began teaching in Maxton, N.C.
1879 One of the founding members of North Carolina Industrial Association, along with brother, Osborne Jr.
1880 Secretary of North Carolina Industrial Association and editor of its publication, Journal of Industry
1881-1884 Worked as clerk in Raleigh Post Office
1888 Teacher in Durham Colored Graded School; editor of Progressive Educator of N.C.
1889 Principal of Garfield Graded School in Raleigh, N.C.; agent for A.S. Barnes and Co. publishers, New York
1890 Principal of Oberlin Graded School in Raleigh, N.C.
1892 Treasurer of North Carolina Industrial Association
1896 Appointed Principal of Garfield School in Raleigh, N.C.
1900 Brother, Osborne, Jr., died
1902 Partner with J. H. Lewis in Inter State Real Estate and Employment Agency, Trenton, N.J.; Principal of Oberlin School in Raleigh, N.C.
1903 Member of the faculty of North Carolina State Colored Normal School, Franklinton, N.C.
1905 Appointed Principal of Colored High School in Raleigh, N.C.; daughter, Eva, died of pneumonia and possible malaria in July; son, Charles, died of illness in December
1906 Appointed Principal of Chavis School in Raleigh, N.C.
1907 Played an active role in preparing the N.C. Negro Exhibit for the Jamestown Exposition; Colored Secretary of the N.C. Commission of the Jamestown Exposition; Secretary of Negro Development and Exposition Co. of USA; Superintendent of the Raleigh Branch of the North Carolina Mutual and Provident Association
1908 Traveling Agent of the North Carolina Mutual and Provident Association; Member of the North Carolina Republican Executive Committee
1910 Editor of Our Advance, a paper in Raleigh; Principal of Public School, Method, N.C.
1915 Leading figure in building of Berry O'Kelly Training School (previously known as Method School) in Method, N.C.; served as the school's principal
1916 Secretary of N.C. Republican Executive Committee
1917 Editor of Raleigh Independent
1918 Moved to Portsmouth, Va. in Jun.; served as foreman for laborers in the Norfolk Navy Yard
1921 Moved back to Raleigh, N.C.; again made editor of Raleigh Independent
1922 Assigned teaching position at Pleasant Hill School, Garner, N.C.
1923 Served as Principal of Haywood High School in Haywood, N.C. (Chatham County); Principal of Horton Public School in Pittsboro, N.C.; wife, Eliza, died after stroke
1924 Appointed Principal of Booker T. Washington School in Wilson's Mills, N.C. (Johnson County)
1926 Served as teacher in Manchester, N.C.
1927 Served as teacher in Bridge, N.C.
1928 Author of review of Negro Life in North Carolina with My Recollections
1931 Died in Raleigh, Sept. 4; survived by daughters, Emma Hunter Satterwhite and Lena M. Hunter
Collection Overview
The Charles N. Hunter Papers date from the 1850s to 1932 and consist of Hunter's personal and professional correspondence, scrapbooks of clippings, articles, reports, and memorabilia. Correspondence relates to personal and financial matters, as well as to Hunter's various activities to improve African American education and economic well-being, particularly in the South. Specific topics touched on throughout his papers include race relations, voting rights, creating an educational system for African Americans, the temperance movement, reconstruction, African American business and agriculture, the North Carolina Industrial Association, and the North Carolina Negro State Fair. The three correspondence subseries form almost half of the Personal and Professional Papers Series. The correspondence subseries are: Business/Community Incoming Correspondence, Personal Incoming Correspondence, and Outgoing Correspondence. Among the correspondents are several African American Congressional representatives such as George H. White and Henry P. Cheatham; major political figures like Franklin D. Roosevelt and John Alexander Logan; important African American scholars including W.E.B. DuBois and Booker T. Washington; and many North Carolina governors, in particular Zebulon B. Vance, Charles B. Aycock, Locke Craig, and Thomas Walter Bickett. Although these letters address professional and political issues, Hunter established friendships with many of the noteable correspondents. The incoming correspondence has been arranged into letters pertaining to Hunter's business or community activities and letters relating to Hunter's personal life. There are also numerous drafts and copies of outgoing correspondence that Hunter wrote.
In the Other Professional Papers Subseries, there is a variety of miscellaneous printed materials and papers that cover Hunter's career as a teacher and principal, involvement in the N.C. Industrial Association, and role in the N.C. Negro State Fair. Included in this subseries is an array of print materials that provide a view of African American life in the South. This includes commencement invitations from historically black colleges and universities, a fourth edition of Lunsford Lane's slave narrative, and newspaper clippings. The bulk of this subseries deals with the larger Raleigh area, though some items address national issues.
The Writings and Speeches Subseries includes addresses given by Hunter and others. Most noteable is a transcription of Frederick Douglass' speech given at the 2nd Annual N.C. Negro State Fair. Amongst Hunter's writings are several pieces intended for a local encyclopedia which detail historic locales and important North Carolina men. Writings cover topics such as African American voting rights and post-Reconstruction analysis. Overall, Hunter's writings provide historical sketches of important figures, events, and reprecussions with an emphasis on local history.
The Scrapbooks Series is made up of seventeen scrapbooks assembled by Hunter which contain clippings and other items concerning race relations and other social, political, and economic affairs pertaining to African Americans. They are composed principally of newspaper clippings published in North Carolina, but their scope is national as well as local. The clippings have been copied and arranged chronologically; the originals are closed to use.
Collection Arrangement
Arranged into the following series and subseries: Personal and Professional Papers Series, organized into the following subseries: Business/Community Incoming Correspondence, Personal Incoming Correspondence, Outgoing Correspondence, Writings and Speeches, and Other Professional Papers) and Scrapbooks.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Aycock, Charles B. (Charles Brantley), 1859-1912
Bickett, Thomas Walter, 1869-1921
Borah, William Edgar, 1865-1940
Cheatham, Henry Plummer, 1857-1935
Craig, Locke, 1860-1925
Dawes, Charles Gates, 1865-1951
Douglass, Frederick, 1818-1895 -- Speeches
Du Bois, W. E. B. (William Edward Burghardt), 1868-1963
Hunter, Charles N., circa 1851-1931
Lane, Lunsford, b. 1803
Logan, John Alexander, 1826-1886
Overman, Lee S. (Lee Slater), 1854-1930
Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945
Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919
Sumner, Charles, 1811-1874
Vance, Zebulon Baird, 1830-1894
Washington, Booker T., 1856-1915
White, George H. (George Henry), 1852-1918
North Carolina Industrial Association
North Carolina State Fair -- History
African American business enterprises -- North Carolina
African American farmers -- North Carolina
African American teachers -- North Carolina
African American teachers -- Correspondence
African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History
African Americans -- Education -- North Carolina
African Americans -- North Carolina -- Social conditions -- To 1964
African Americans -- History
Educators -- Correspondence
Educators -- North Carolina -- Raleigh
Fairs -- North Carolina -- Raleigh
Freedmen -- North Carolina
Racism -- United States -- History
Reconstruction (U.S. history, 1865-1877)
Temperance -- United States -- History -- 19th century.
Durham (N.C.) -- History
North Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950
North Carolina -- Social conditions
North Carolina -- Race relations
Scrapbooks
Related Material
North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850-2008 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Personal and Professional Papers Series, 1861-1931 and undated, (7 boxes)
  The papers of Charles N. Hunter are divided into five subseries: Incoming Business/Community Correspondence; Incoming Personal Correspondence; Outgoing Correspondence; Writings and Speeches; and Other Professional Papers.
  - Incoming Business/Community Correspondence Subseries, 1871-1931, and undated
    This subseries contains a variety of correspondence that reflects the wide array of community and business organizations with which Hunter associated. There is a significant amount of material concerning the education of blacks in rural North Carolina during the late 19th and early 20th centuries, including letters from the Superintendent of Public Instruction of Wake County, Zebulon Judd, and Edward Moses. Contains material demonstrating Hunter's instrumental role in the North Carolina Industrial Association, which was responsible for organizing the N.C. Negro State Fairs in the late 1800s and early 1900s. Correspondence from each of the three founders of North Carolina Mutual (J. Merrick, A.M. Moore, and C.C. Spaulding), and this collection includes material regarding early business practices within N.C. Mutual. Hunter often wrote to a wide variety of government officials, and received letters from senators, representatives, and heads of departments (not limited to Sen. Blache K. Bruce [1879, 1886], Franklin D. Roosevelt [1920] and Theodore Roosevelt, Jr. [1921][as Asst. Secretaries of the Navy]). Hunter also kept up frequent correspondence with the presidents of North Carolina's historically black colleges and universities, such as Shaw University, Negro Agricultural and Technical College of N.C. (currently N.C. A & T University), State Normal School of North Carolina (currently the University of North Carolina at Greensboro) and St. Augustine's College. Contains material demonstrating Hunter's efforts as an advocate for black agricultural laborers, as well as his political efforts to encourage black voter turnout, census enumeration, and the outcomes of U.S. Senate confirmations of presidential appointments. This subseries also includes correspondence from Booker T. Washington [1886, 1909, 1914] regarding funding for black schools, John H. Smyth [1879](U.S. Ambassador to the Republic of Liberia) following a request for a contribution to the N.C. Negro State Fair, and W.E.B. DuBois [1898] soliciting help in an upcoming sociological study, among many others.
    - North Carolina Industrial Association, 1886 March, August-October (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - North Carolina Industrial Association, 1886 October (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - North Carolina Industrial Association, 1886 November-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1871-1891 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1886-1903 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1891-1900 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1901-1902 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1902-1903 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1904-1906 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1907 January-April (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1907 May-July (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1907 August-1909 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence, 1910-1914 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1910-1926 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1916-1917 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence regarding Hunter's discharge from work in the Navy, complaint against the discharge, and Navy's final disposition, 1921 January-May (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1924 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1925-1926 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1927-1928 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1929-1931 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Incoming Personal Correspondence Subseries, 1869-1931 and undated
    Contains a large quantity of incoming correspondence from family, friends, and former students, including significant correspondence with nephew, Edward Hunter, and daughters, as well as Hunter's son-in-law and former minister, James K. Satterwhite. Also contains some material pertaining to personal financial matters.
    - Personal correspondence, 1869-1874, 1882-1890 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Personal correspondence, 1892-1903 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Personal correspondence, 1904-1909 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Personal correspondence, 1910-1914 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Personal correspondence, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Personal correspondence, 1918-1920 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Personal correspondence, 1921-1922 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Personal correspondence, 1923 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Personal correspondence, 1924-1925 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Personal correspondence, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Personal correspondence, 1928-1931 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Letters from or regarding family, undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Personal correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Personal correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Legal-size personal correspondence, 1927-1928 and undated, including photograph of Robert Milton Braan, age 5 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Birch bark letter, 18-- (Opaperfolder 1)
      [Restricted: needs conservation work before access can be granted. Please contact reference archivist for access to this item.]
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1871-1931 and undated
    Contains various drafts of letters written by Hunter to various individuals. Includes drafts of letters to Mary Church Terrell, U.S. presidents, and North Carolina education administrators.
    - Correspondence, 1871-1877, 1886 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1889-1890, 1897-1909 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1910-1920 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1921-1926 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1927-1931 and undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Other Professional Papers Subseries, 1850s-1931 and undated
    A variety of papers such as pamphlets, programs, receipts, gradebooks and other school records, and ephemera such as program tickets and invitations. The earliest item dated in the 1850s is a blank slave life insurance application from the North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company (Raleigh, N.C.). Also of note is the fourth edition of a slave narrative attributed to former slave Lunsford Lane of Raleigh, N.C., originally published in 1841. Many of the documents relate to the N.C. Negro State Fair. Includes biographical sketches of Hunter, as well as papers concerning the 1907 Jamestown Negro Exhibit and the N.C. Industrial Association. Documents are sorted chronologically and foldered by decade within the boxes.
    - Slave Life Insurance Policy, North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1850s, (blank) (Opaperfolder 1)
    - Lunsford Lane, The Narrative of Lunsford Lane, Formerly of Raleigh, N.C. Embracing an Account of his Early life, the Redemption by purchase of himself and family from Slavery, and his Banishment from the place of his birth for the Crime of wearing a Colored skin. Published by himself. Fourth ed. Boston: Hewes and Watson's Print, 1861 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - "Journal of Freedom," 1865 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Ninth Anniversary of the Proclamation of Emancipation invitation, 1872 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Letter from B. F. Moore declining invitation, 1872 January 1 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Letter from National Freedman's Savings and Trust Company, 1872 March 9 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Letter from M. Bryant regarding a land deed, 1873 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Obituary published in The Examiner for Reverend Richard S. Mason, D.D., 1874 February 22 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Teacher's First Grade Certificate, 1878 March 16 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - An Act to Incorporate the N.C. Industrial Association, 1879 March 14 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Teacher's First Grade Certificate, 1879 August 16 (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Letter, June 24, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Notes regarding the Second Session of the East Raleigh School, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - First constitution of the N.C. Industrial Association, 1879 (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Teacher's First Grade Certificate, 1880 November 6 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Note of the Office of the Commissioner of the Freedman's Savings and Trust Company, 1883 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - St. Valentine's Day First Grand Dress Reception invitation, 1884 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Notice of Applicant's Standing from the United States Civil Service Commission, 1884 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - First monthly report of C. Dillard, 1885 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Advertisement regarding research for The Prominent Colored Men of North Carolina, 1885 (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - "Price List of Fair Goods from The Fair Publishing House of Norwalk, Ohio," 1886 February 15 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Receipt for purchased goods from The Fair Publishing House, 1886 September 15 (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - North Carolina Industrial Association contract, 1886 October 11 (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Teacher's First Grade Certificate, 1886 October 16 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Gradebook, 1894 (Box 5, Folder 33)
    - Invitation to the Fourth Annual Closing Exercises, A. and M. College, 1898 May 22-26 (Box 5, Folder 34)
    - "Articles of Agreement regarding property," circa 1901 (Box 5, Folder 35)
    - Installation services at the First Baptist Church, Raleigh, N.C. program, 1902 June 8 (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Oberlin School Progress of Pupils grade book, 1902-1903 (Box 5, Folder 37)
    - Complementary Negro State Fair ticket, 1903 October 27-30 (Box 5, Folder 38)
    - Attendance scrolls for Teachers' Institute, 1903 August 17-22 (Box 5, Folder 39)
    - The Hampton Normal and Agricultural Institute, bill for Eva Hunter, 1904 April 30 (Box 5, Folder 40)
    - The National Association of Teachers of Negro Youth Second Annual Meeting announcement, 1905 June 28-30 (Box 5, Folder 41)
    - Twentieth Annual Convention, Brotherhood of St. Andrew brochure, 1905 September 20-24 (Box 5, Folder 42)
    - "Resolution of Respect. Adopted by St. Ambrose Choir to the memory of Miss Hunter," 1905 July 13 (Box 5, Folder 43)
    - Stock letter soliciting shareholders for a black-owned Durham bank, 1906 February 15 (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - "A Joint Resolution Concerning the Jamestown Exposition," 1907 February 16 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Jamestown Exposition notes, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Letter from Thomas J. Calloway of the Executive Committee of the Jamestown Exposition, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Press release regarding Governor Glenn's speech at the Jamestown Exposition, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - "Negro Semi-Centennial: President Taft Endorsed the Exposition for the Race," Raleigh News and Observer, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Stock letter requesting black-owned newspaper subscriptions for the Jamestown Negro Exhibit, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Letter following Jamestown Exposition from the N.C. Dept. of Negro Development and Exposition, 1907 (Box 5, Folder 51)
    - Lena Hunter's report card, 1907 December 31 (Box 5, Folder 52)
    - Registration form to teach for Wake County, completed by Hunter, 1910 November 12 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Letter, S. Hughes to "My Dear Sister," circa 1910s, 6 February (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Donor cards for the Berry O'Kelly Training and Industrial School Building Fund, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - President Berry O'Kelly's address, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - Financial report, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 57)
    - "North Carolina Negroes Appeal To Do War Work," unknown newspaper, circa 1916 (Box 5, Folder 58)
    - United States Civil Service Commission examination scores of Charles N. Hunter, 1918 May 25 (Box 5, Folder 59)
    - Three news articles from The North Carolina Review, 1920s: "Traces History of Negro in U.S." (Box 5, Folder 60)